Alessandro Rossini

Senior Information Technology Advisor, Researcher, Ph.D.

© Oslo, Norway me@alessandrorossini.org alessandrorossini.org

Alessandro Rossini is a senior information technology advisor. He is advising customers on planning and designing the cloud solutions that best fit their requirements, with particular emphasis on modernisation and innovation.

During recent years, Alessandro has conducted extensive research and development on cloud computing and served as a member of the technical committee of the OASIS TOSCA standard. In his position at EVRY, he is transferring these research results to the industry in order to offer customers a competitive advantage.

Alessandro holds a Ph.D. degree in informatics from the University of Bergen, Norway, and an M.Sc. degree in computer science from the University of L'Aquila, Italy. He has lived in three countries and speaks English, Norwegian, Italian, and Spanish. His colleagues describe him as detail-oriented, organised, and goal-oriented.

Experience

Senior Cloud Advisor, EVRY Cloud Services, Oslo, Norway

2017-

Advising customers on planning and designing the cloud solutions that best fit their requirements, with particular emphasis on modernisation and innovation. Subject matter expert in large bids and projects with third-party vendors.

Research Scientist, Dep. of Software and Service Innovation, SINTEF, Oslo, Norway

2012–2017
Research on model-driven engineering and cloud computing. Development of CAMEL, a domain-specific modelling language along with a models@run-time environment for specifying provisioning, deployment, monitoring, and orchestration of cross-cloud applications at design-time and their enactment at run-time. Development of mechanisms for failure analysis and failure prevention and recovery of cloud applications. Internal project manager and work package leader in the EU-funded projects PaaSage, Broker@Cloud, and ARCADIA, and the SINTEF-funded project STWT (see Projects below). Technical committee member of the OASIS Topology and Orchestration Specification for Cloud Applications (TOSCA) and co-chair of the TOSCA Instance Model Ad Hoc group. Organising and program committee member in international conferences and workshops. Supervision of students in the context of Master thesis and internship.

·	
Part-time Lecturer, Dep. of Electrical and Electronic Eng., Bergen University College, Norway	2012
Guest Researcher, Dep. of Computer Science, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Spain	2011
Research Fellow, Dep. of Informatics, University of Bergen, Norway	2008-2011
Software Engineer, Integrator, Bergen, Norway	2007
Software Engineer, ZeroNotice, L'Aquila, Italy	2005-2007
Projects	
ARCADIA, a framework for developing highly distributed applications	2014-2016
PaaSage, a model-based framework for specifying and executing cross-cloud applications	2012-2016
Broker@Cloud, a cloud brokerage framework for quality assurance and optimisation	2012-2016
STWT, a framework for specifying simulators for systems of partial differential equations	2013-2014
DPF, a diagrammatic specification framework founded on category theory	2008-2012
ZNF, an open source framework for developing enterprise web applications	2005-2007
Education	
Philosophiae Doctor (Ph.D.), Dep. of Informatics, University of Bergen, Norway	2011
Master of Science (M.Sc.), Dep. of Computer Science, Università degli Studi dell'Aquila, Italy	2006
Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Dep. of Computer Science, Università degli Studi dell'Aquila, Italy	2003

Languages

Mothertongue: Italian, Fluent: English, Norwegian, Spanish

Publications

30+ publications in peer-reviewed conferences and journals.